<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The late good successe and victory, which it pleased God to giue to some of the King of Bohemia's forces, vnder the conduct of the prince of Anhalt, generall for the said King, against the two great generals of the Emperour, Bucquoy and Dampiere, atchieued neare Horne in Austria VVith many other considerable things concerning the affaires of that countrey. Vnto which is added the articles of agreement, made betweene the said King of Bohemia and Bethlem Gaber, prince of Hungaria and Transiluania.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 30KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B13640</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99856391</idno>
  <idno type="VID">177245</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2264219662</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 11356</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S121206</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99856391e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B13640)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 177245)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 957:4, 1023:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The late good successe and victory, which it pleased God to giue to some of the King of Bohemia's forces, vnder the conduct of the prince of Anhalt, generall for the said King, against the two great generals of the Emperour, Bucquoy and Dampiere, atchieued neare Horne in Austria VVith many other considerable things concerning the affaires of that countrey. Vnto which is added the articles of agreement, made betweene the said King of Bohemia and Bethlem Gaber, prince of Hungaria and Transiluania.</title>
                  <author>Bohemia (Kingdom). Treaties, etc. Transylvania.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[20]; [24] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Abraham Schilders [i.e. William Jones? or William Stansby?],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Middleburg [i.e. London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.D.C.XX. [1620]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Apparently by the same printer as STC 10814 (STC).</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴ C² ; A-C⁴.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>"Articles of the league, made betweene Fredericke, King of Bohemia .. and .. Gabriel, Prince of Hungaria and Transiluania .." (dated at end "the 15. of Ianuarie 1620") has separate dated title page and register. It was also issued separately as STC 11349.</note>
                  <note>"Articles" identified as STC 11349 on UMI microfilm reel 957.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
                  <note>Appears at reel 957 (Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery copy, part 2 only) and at reel 1023 (Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery copy, part 1 only).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Thirty Years' War, 1618-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Bohemia (Czech Republic) --  History --  1618-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:177245:1"/>
            <p>ARTICLES OF THE LEAGVE, MADE BETWEENE FREDERICKE, King of Bohemia, Count Palatine of the Rhine, Elector of the sacred Empire, Duke of Baua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria, Marquis of Morauia, Duke of Silesia and Luxemburg, Marquis of the higher and lower Lusatia, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And the High and Mightie Prince GABRIEL, Prince of Hungaria and Transiluania, Moldauia, Valachia, and Earle of Siculen, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Together with the States of the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said Kingdome, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>M.D.C.XX.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treaty">
            <pb facs="tcp:177245:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177245:2"/>
            <head>Articles of the League, made betweene FREDERICK King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> Count Palatine of the <hi>Rhine,</hi> Elector of the sacred Empire, Duke of <hi>Bauaria,</hi> Marquis of <hi>Morauia,</hi> Duke of <hi>Silesia</hi> and <hi>Luxemburg,</hi> Marquis of the higher and lower <hi>Luzatia, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <head>And the high and mightie Prince, GABRIEL, Prince of <hi>Hungaria</hi> and <hi>Transiluania, Moldauia, Valachia,</hi> and Earle of <hi>Siculen, &amp;c.</hi> Together with the States of the aforesaid Kingdomes, &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>IN the Name of the most holy and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>separable Trinitie, GOD the <hi>Father,</hi> the <hi>Sonne,</hi> and the <hi>Holy Ghost;</hi> the most Wise, Righteous, and mightie Ruler of all Lords, Princes, and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, to whom bee all honour and prayse eternally. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </opener>
            <opener>
               <signed>We, FREDERICKE, by the grace of God, King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> Count Palatine of the <hi>Rhine,</hi> Elector of the sacred Empire; Duke of <hi>Bauaria,</hi> Marquis of <hi>Morauia,</hi> Duke of <hi>Silesia</hi> and <hi>Luxemburg,</hi> Marquis of the higher and lower <hi>Lusatia, &amp;c.</hi>
               </signed>
               <salute>Send greeting to the said famous Realme of <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemia,</hi> the Margraueship of <hi>Morauia,</hi> the Dukedom of <hi>Silesia,</hi> the vpper and neather Margraueship of <hi>Luzatia</hi> (as incorpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Prouinces with the said Kingdome) and to the higher and lower States of the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dukedomes of <hi>Austria,</hi> and to all and euery
<pb facs="tcp:177245:3"/>one of them in particular, to whom these Presents shal or may in any wise appertaine:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>signifying vnto them, That although ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny yeeres since there hath beene a strong and perfect bond of confederacie, vnitie, peace, and league, had and held from time to time, betweene the famous Kingdome of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> together with the incorporated and vnited Prouinces thereof, and the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Kingdome of <hi>Hungaria,</hi> as sufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appeareth by diuers and seuerall Treaties made and held in <hi>Vienna, Presburg,</hi> and elsewhere, whereof, on both sides, Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings and Articles were drawne, made, and written, which both parties, long time in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiolably and firmely haue held, obserued, &amp; maintayned, vntill certayne turbulent and vnquiet persons, haue sought and practized to set variance betweene them, thereby to breake and dissolue their said League and perfect Vnitie. Whereupon, the States of the Kingdome of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> and the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graueship of <hi>Morauia,</hi> by their Ambassa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors, did most friendly certifie the Prince of <hi>Transiluania,</hi> for that time being, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the States of the Kingdome of <hi>Hungaria,</hi> not only long since in the raigns of the Emperours, <hi>Rodulphus</hi> and <hi>Matthias,</hi> of famous memorie, deceased, to certifie
<pb facs="tcp:177245:3"/>them that then were assembled and had met together, to agree vpon, and to make a firme League of Amitie betweene them, but now also presently haue sought vnto and desired them, that touching the earnest renewing, strengthening and better confirmation of their said ancient League and Amity, they would not withdraw, nor shew themselues backward. Which insinuation (as it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth) being friendly and willingly accepted and liked of by them, Wee also hauing a great desire thereunto, (beeing perswaded that we haue not wel performed our charge, duty, touching the furtherance &amp; aduance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the said Confederation betweene the said Kingdomes and Prouinces) vnlesse we shew our selues wholly desirous and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted to the said renewing, restoring, and declaration of the said often desired league, as also to shew that thankefulnesse and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuity which we are bound to yeeld vnto the famous Prince of <hi>Hungaria</hi> and <hi>Transilua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,</hi> and the States of the said Countreyes, for hauing vouchsafed at such times as wee were oppressed with troubles and Warres, to send vs aide.</p>
            <p>Therefore to requite the same, We haue not beene slacke, willingly to consent, and
<pb facs="tcp:177245:4"/>agree vnto their request and desires, that by the aide and helpe of God, this religious, fruitfull, most commendable and profitable worke, for all Christendome, according to all good Christians desires, might happily proceed and goe forward, and the League by certaine necessary Couenants renewed, increased, and strengthned, (by the Articles insuing) with the famous Prince <hi>Gabriel,</hi> by the Grace of God, Prince of <hi>Hungaria,</hi> and <hi>Transiluania,</hi> Earle of <hi>Siculen,</hi> and the States of the famous Kingdome of <hi>Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria,</hi> then assembled in <hi>Presburg,</hi> vpon the ordinary day of assembly there holden, (his said Maiesty giuing his Princely word and assurance, touching the same, with full au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, for and in the name of the States of the Principalitie of <hi>Transiluania,</hi> and the three Nations; for that by reason of the distance of places, and longnesse of the way, they could not send their speciall and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Ambassadors) made by the most No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, Honorable, Valiant, wise, and discreet persons, <hi>George Fredericke,</hi> Earle of <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enboe,</hi> Baron of <hi>Langenbrucke, Boleslauia, Cosmenes,</hi> and <hi>Krulich,</hi> one of ours and the Kingdome of <hi>Bohemia's</hi> counsell of warre, Generall of the Armie, Colonell of three
<pb facs="tcp:177245:4"/>thousand footmen, and a thousand Horse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and Knights. <hi>Henry Matthias,</hi> Earle of <hi>Thueryn,</hi> Baron of <hi>Crutz, Willisch,</hi> and <hi>Lestdorf,</hi> Burgraue of the Castle of <hi>Carolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stem,</hi> one of ours, and the Kingdome of <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemia's</hi> Councell, Chiefe Generall of the Campe, and Colonell of three thousand footmen. <hi>Leonardus Colonum,</hi> free Baron of <hi>Fels</hi> and <hi>Scheuckenberch,</hi> Baron of <hi>Engls<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourgh, Buchauw, Schenauw,</hi> and <hi>Hacheru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stein,</hi> Marshall of the Armie, Captaine of six hundred Horsemen. <hi>Iohannes van Bub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> Lord of <hi>Tzwischij,</hi> and <hi>Boranictzij</hi> Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geant Maior, and Colonell of a thousand Horsemen. <hi>Paul Wostersby Kaeplerum,</hi> Lord of <hi>Sulewctz, Wotizcij,</hi> and <hi>Salutzsi</hi> Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell of the <hi>Ingeners,</hi> and of fifteene hundred Footmen. <hi>Paul Gsehinium</hi> of <hi>Pragh,</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuer for the States and Kingdomes of <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemia. Iohannes,</hi> Baron of <hi>Wurben,</hi> Lord of <hi>Wlassenie, Lateni, Brudetz,</hi> and <hi>Biscu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitz. Paul Wolbram,</hi> Lord of <hi>Frisbergh,</hi> Prouinciall Burgraue of the Margraueship of <hi>Morauia. Bernardus Tzastriziel</hi> in <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mischt, Fredericus Meniardus,</hi> and <hi>Georgius Millerus</hi> Counsellors of <hi>Inuimands,</hi> in the Marquisate of <hi>Morauia.</hi> For the Duke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Silesia,</hi> and the States of the two
<pb facs="tcp:177245:5"/>Margraueship of <hi>Luzatia,</hi> because they for the distance of the places, and length of the way, could not send their speciall Ambassa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors hether, (for whom the Kings Maiestie of <hi>Bohemia</hi> giueth his Princely word, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth their Commission vpon him with full authority.) The Lord <hi>Erasmus van Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dauw,</hi> free Baron of <hi>Haus,</hi> and <hi>Rapelstein; Andreas Thonardi,</hi> free Baron of <hi>Theru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bergh;</hi> and <hi>Rechbergh,</hi> Lord of <hi>Ouerhas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>singh; Georgius Christopherus, Rouberus</hi> Lord of <hi>Reinegk Obrem, Trixen, Zacha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium,</hi> and <hi>Stanzerum,</hi> Iudge of the Prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Law in neather <hi>Austria, Georgius Eras<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> Baron of <hi>Tseruembl,</hi> Chiefe Sewer of the Dukedome of <hi>Carnolia,</hi> and Margraue of <hi>Sclauonia; Iohannes Ortolpheus Tezman</hi> of <hi>Geylsbach,</hi> and <hi>Freidenegk,</hi> and <hi>Bal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sarus Klesselboden,</hi> Counsellors of <hi>Steinen,</hi> Ambassadours for both the Arch-Duke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of <hi>Austria,</hi> sent with full and suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent power to the said Parliament, in the Kingdome of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> We consulted, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed, and concluded as followeth.</p>
            <p>First, That continuall, perpetuall and an inseparable league of vnity, peace, &amp; friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly amity, shall bee holden, and truely and vprightly maintained, and obserued, from
<pb facs="tcp:177245:5"/>henceforth by and between the Kingdome of <hi>Bohemia.</hi> The Margraueship of <hi>Morauia,</hi> The Dukedome of <hi>Silesia,</hi> the vpper and neather Margraueships of <hi>Luzatia,</hi> and the States thereof, as Prouinces incorporated one with the other, and consequently, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene, and with the true Kings of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> Margraues, Dukes, Barons, and their Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessors, as also betweene the higher and lower Arch-Dukedomes of <hi>Austria,</hi> and the States thereof, that now are or hereafter shal bee, and the King or Prince of <hi>Hungaria,</hi> and the Kingdomes and Prouinces annexed to the said Crowne. The Prince of <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siluania,</hi> and those parts of the Kingdome of <hi>Hungaria,</hi> now annexed to the said Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalitie of <hi>Transiluania,</hi> as also with all the States thereof, that now are, and which hereafter shall bee.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, If at any time hereafter, (by what Enemy soeuer procured) the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and mutuall peace shall be perturbed, by inuading of the Kingdomes or Prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the said Confederates, directly or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>directly, contrary to their said League, or if any of them, deceitfull breaking off from the said League, or the Participants therein, shall inuade vs or any of them, that then wee
<pb facs="tcp:177245:6"/>shalbe holden &amp; bound, with all our means, and power, and also with our liues, and the shedding of our dearest bloud, to ayde, helpe, and assist each other, in and for the maintenance of this our League and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federacy, and therein and for the same bee ready to liue and die. Neuerthelesse, with such preparation and power as the necessity of the case of either side requireth, or shall require, and shall in time be requested as in the future common agreement of the said confederated Kingdomes and Prouinces, specially concerning the defence thereof, shall be concluded and set downe.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thirdly, all of vs shall take and haue a speciall and earnest care for the aduance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and inlarging of this Confederation, by accepting the alliance of the Countreyes bordering about vs, that so it may bee more and more strengthened, but not without the knowledge, will, and common counsell and consent of the Confederates, vpon conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that those Countreyes, that are desirous and seeke to be admitted into this League, shall first be bound with the like Oath and promise that wee are, and that being done, shalbe participants of the ayde, freedom, &amp; profit therof, as other Kingdomes and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces, cōtained in the said League, noware.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:177245:6"/>
            <p n="4">4. Fourthly, The Articles of agreement in this inuiolable and perpetuall Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, made betweene the said Kingdomes, Prouinces, and States thereof, and in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe of their Heires and Successours, shall as well by vs that are now liuing, as by our said Heires and Successors for better and surer maintenance thereof, vpon euery day of generall meeting, be repeated, rehearsed, and openly read in Court, and presence of of the Assembly. And likewise, euery fift yeere at a certaine time and peace, with the consent of all the Confederates, order shall bee taken for the meeting and common as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembling of the said Confederates, at the which Assembly, all such disorders and controuersies, as by chance shall formerly haue bin cōmitted &amp; happen, touching the maintenance of the Articles and contents thereof, may in time be holpen and preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or as the state, necessitie and conuenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of the time requireth, may be augmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and made manifest and cleerer.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Fiftly, Without the knowledge, will &amp; consent, of the confederated Kingdomes and Prouinces, it shall not be lawfull for any of vs, to make any offensiue or defensiue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration, yet if any Inuasion be made in any
<pb facs="tcp:177245:7"/>of the said Kingdomes or Prouinces, or that any towne feared of inuasion, to be made by the enemie, that bordereth vpon any of the Confederates, shall happen, before any helpe may bee had, or proceed from the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther confederated Prouinces, or that they may haue intelligence thereof, in that case, it shall be lawfull for any of the said confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derated Kingdomes and Prouinces, in the meane time, to defend themselues by armes against the enemy, as well as they can. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, it shall not be lawfull for any of vs, particularly of our selues, to make peace or truce with any new or future enemy and disturbers of the common peace, of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporated Kingdomes and confederated Prouinces, as defenders of them, our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federacie leauing the rest of their Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates, without the licence and consent of the rest of the said confederates. And com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon &amp; solemne peace being agreed vpon, those persons shall therein be contayned, that for the publike seruice (either politike or marshal) haue vsed all the diligence they could, for the aduancement of the said king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and Prouinces. It shall also not be granted nor permitted to any of the Kings, Princes, and Lords (without the leaue and
<pb facs="tcp:177245:7"/>good will) of the said Kingdomes and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces, to begin any open warre, much lesse to put or place any strange Souldiers into garrison in any of the said confederated Townes, Kingdomes, and Prouinces, nor to permit any troupe or troupes of Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers to passe through their Countries, Townes, or Prouinces, or to licence them to depart.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Forasmuch as that the said King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes and Prouinces, can by no meanes be preserued and vpholden, vnlesse the bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and passages of the Kingdome of <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garia</hi> be maintayned and defended. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, We the said King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> and the States of the same Kingdome, together with the aforesaid incorporated Prouinces, as also of vpper and lower <hi>Austria,</hi> conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, that at this time the state of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is yet very vnquiet, and the greatest part thereof laid waste and ouer-run, and that We, with the great costs and charges of our Armie, are continually burthened, and are likely daily to haue more burthens and troubles fall vpon vs, yet to shew forth the cause of our true and willing assistance, Wee will from hence forth continue that payment, which before this time yeerely
<pb facs="tcp:177245:8"/>hath beene ordinarily and vsually paid to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Garrisons, and the maintenance of the Marches and Borders of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Hungaria,</hi> by euery confederate Prouince or Countrie, according to their portion. Which also in the next generall Assembly of the Confederates, shall bee truely set downe, and made knowne. But hauing better considered of the welfare of the common cause, Wee are content to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease the said summe with the value of fifty thousand Dollers of 70. Krutzers the peece, in ready money. But yet that it shall be held, reckoned, and accounted, to proceed only from Our good wills and neighbourhoods, for the maintenance and securitie of the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid Kingdoms and Prouinces, and that the said summe shall not be employed, but only for the payment of the Garrisons, and the defence of the Borders of the same, as also that there shall bee certayne Commis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sioners appointed specially to looke vnto it. And if it shall so fall out, that the said Bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders shall haue any need or occasion (as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ready to decay) to be repayred and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified, We will not be slacke (as Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates) to enlarge and encrease some contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution towards the same, as by friendly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest
<pb facs="tcp:177245:8"/>made by the Lords of <hi>Hungaria,</hi> shall be motioned and desired.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Seuenthly, specially, and before all things it is necessary, that peace should not bee renewed with the Turke, but only an ambassage, motion, and treatie; agreed vpon and constantly continued, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore from all the Kingdomes and confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated Prouinces, there shall be some sent to the <hi>Ottomans</hi> countrey, to renew, deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine vpon, and strengthen the said peace. Touching the counsell, and furthering of this good and most necessary businesse, his Maiestie hath of himselfe vndertaken the care and proceeding thereof, and to send his particular ambassage, as also that ours of the Kingdome of <hi>Bohemia</hi> and the Prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces bordering vpon it, shall goe with it, and that then euery one for his part take order for and prepare the Presents, and other costs and charges, that shal be necessary and conuenient, for the setting forth of the same ambassage.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Eightly, the confederated Princes &amp; Lords, to shew their good and true neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourhood, to their Confederates &amp; Allies, will take care presently in the beginning of Lent (if no waightie and important hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance
<pb facs="tcp:177245:9"/>thereunto doth not in the meane time happen) by certayne Cōmissioners on both sides equally thereunto appointed, to ratifie and confirme the Borders of the Kingdome of <hi>Hungaria, Morauia, Silesia,</hi> and <hi>Austria,</hi> for the which there hath beene so long and continuall strife.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Ninthly, vpon request made by his Maiestie, and the States of the Kingdome of <hi>Hungaria,</hi> touching the good of those of <hi>Austria</hi> (to the great hinderance of the Kingdome of <hi>Hungaria</hi>) vntill this time with-holden (although true members of the said Kingdome) and now at last againe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriated to the said Kingdome of <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garia:</hi> The confederated Princes, to signifie their good neighbourhood and confedera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, will take order, that things shall bee brought to a good conclusion, and will therein bee Mediators and helpefull, that the same may be restored againe.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Tenthly, In the confederated Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces and Kingdomes, in euery place, when and where they will, they shall all hold ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall meetings and assemblies, with this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect, notwithstanding, that the Lawes, Freedomes, Priuileges, and ancient Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stomes of the particular Kingdomes, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces
<pb facs="tcp:177245:9"/>States, Townes, Commonalties, and Persons of the same, shall on both sides bee maintayned and obserued.</p>
            <p n="11">11. Eleuenthly, that the bond of amitie betweene the Confederates may bee the stronger: The value of the Mint shall bee made alike in the said Kingdomes, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federated Prouinces, and the Moneyes with good correspondence &amp; limitation on both sides, Minted: and that in the next generall assembly of all the Confederates, in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient place (after the assembly of the whole Kingdoms) a certaine limitation and taxe shall be made of the greater moneyes, and that the smaller moneyes and the gros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sest, shall hold all one course, whereof it shall bee needfull that a Publication should be made in all Kingdomes.</p>
            <p n="12">12. Twelftly, If in processe of time any difference or question, touching the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract of the League, should chance to hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen; the confederated Kingdomes and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces, vpon request made by one of the said parties, shall appoint a place, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto all of them comming, the controuersie shall be declared, and the difficultie thereof being decided, it shall (by the order and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right proceeding of the said Confederates) be determined: and there it shall be requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,
<pb facs="tcp:177245:10"/>and by either side appointed, in a cause necessarily concerning them, as aforesaid, that the said partie Plaintife, vpon request made by the Confederates, shall vpon the general day of Parlament or Assembly, send thither their speciall ambassage. To the end, that any such waightie difference, which by chance may happen among the confedera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Kingdomes and Prouinces, may openly and speedily be agreed vpon and ended: and in <hi>Hungaria,</hi> the King, Prince Palatine, and the Councell of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> &amp; other confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated Lords, shalbe appointed as Protectors in that case, and in whom the fault shall first be found, to appease and pacifie the same.</p>
            <p n="13">13. Thirteenthly, That by a most strict and perpetuall Law it shall be ordayned and prohibited, that in no places of the confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derated kingdomes and Prouinces, there shall be any Iesuites permitted to reside, nor be resident; neither that any man, of what state or condition soeuer he be, man or wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, high or low, vnder any pretence or shew whatsoeuer, secretly or openly shall vphold, maintayne, entertayne, or harbour any of them, much lesse vse them in any ambassage, either spirituall or temporall, for the Commonwealth; neither that any King, Prince, or any of the States in their particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar
<pb facs="tcp:177245:10"/>places, shall vse their counsell or aduice; that also they shall not bee preferred to any dignitie, vnder what pretence soeuer they shall be called thereunto, vpon payne of notable dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyaltie and perpetuall banishment. The execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion whereof shall bee referred to the States of the Kingdome or Prouince, wherein the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, in this case, shall haue had his residence.</p>
            <p n="14">14. Fourteenthly, When any helpe for the warre, or protection against any enemie of the confederated Kingdomes and Prouinces, shall be required and sought for, and to that end be sent into this Kingdome, or to the confederated Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces, the chiefe Commanders shall haue their dependance from the King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> the Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graue, the principal Captaynes of the Prouinces, Presidents, Collonels, and generall Captaynes, and shall proceed in their affaires against the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy by common consent. And such Souldiers as are sent to aide them, shall certainly bee paid by them that sent them, and thereby bee held in better order, seruice, gouernment, &amp; obedience, that they may not haue any pretence or seeme to be sent, rather for the spoyling and ouer throw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, then the defending, of the Gentlemen, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people, and the Countrie: and specially, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the confederacy, they must not bee suffered to spoile Noblemens houses, free towns, Churches, Parishes, and Hospitals. And lastly,
<pb facs="tcp:177245:11"/>that all such shall by the confederated Lords in their owne Kingdomes and Prouinces, bee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired after, and discharged of their seruice.</p>
            <p n="15">15. We haue thought it good and conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, as also the other Lords of the confederacie, that if any books of the affaires of the Kings pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledges, or any written Copies, touching the Kingdome and the confederated Prouinces, in former times kept in any place (especially after the restitution of the holy Crowne of the Kings of <hi>Hungaria</hi>) in <hi>Bohemia,</hi> or in <hi>Austria,</hi> or that may there be found, that speedily, vpon the first request made, all and euery one of them shall be giuen againe, and without any delay truly deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered to the States to whom they belong.</p>
            <p n="16">16. And that among vs, all mutuall fidelity, friendship, good will, and diligent neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood and confederated League, may bee obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and vpholden. If at this present there be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hostilitie, betweene, or among the confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated Kings, Princes, kingdomes, Prouinces, and their States, and Inhabitants, from this time forward, it shall, and must be wholly ended, and for euer left off and forgotten.</p>
            <p n="17">17. And if any man shall presently or here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after be iudged to be banished, from, or out of one kingdome or Prouince of the Confederates, he shall not be receaued into, nor entertayned in any other of the kingdomes or Prouinces in the
<pb facs="tcp:177245:11"/>said Confederacie, but in like sort shall bee ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished from thence: And further, in all the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sederated kingdomes, hee shall bee held and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted to be a banished man, and it shall not auaile him, that without the knowledge of the other kingdomes and Prouinces, he hath againe beene pardoned and receiued into grace and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour (nouerthelesse, reseruing the authoritie of Kings and Princes, of restoring such persons a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine into the grace and fauour of their king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes and Prouinces, with the consent of the States thereof.) But if any such banished person or offender, shall chance to haue fled into, and faued himselfe in any of the confederated king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes or Prouinces, and shall therein be found, the principalest of that Kingdome or Prouince, shall (as aforesaid) bee bound, without any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception or excuse, simply and truly, to send that banished and wicked person, to that kingdome or prouince, wherein hee receaued that iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of banishment and punishment.</p>
            <p>Lastly, Euery King or Prince (now, or in time to come) of the kingdomes and Prouinces, that haue made and confirmed this League of confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deracy, and promised that they will doe their best to vphold and maintayne the same, and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne his kingdome accordingly, shall by their force, power, and protection, proceeding from the same, with the consent of the States thereof,
<pb facs="tcp:177245:12"/>freely vse the same against all their enemies. And if contrary to all hope and meaning, any of them both, against the freedome of Religion and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique priuiledges therein granted, shall doe to the contrarie, thereby seeks to subuert and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw them; in that case the States thereof shall be free and discharged of their homage and oath of fidelitie, and shall haue full power and perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual authoritie to speake against them and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist them, &amp; for that cause shall not by any man bee blamed or accused of treason: and for the maintayning of this Confederacy, by all and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery particular person that is receaued therein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, as aforesaid, the King or Prince, at the so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnisation of his coronation, shall take a so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne oath, that he will hold and maintayne the same, and be bound thereunto.</p>
            <p>Therefore, We the aforesaid King of <hi>Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia,</hi> and all the States of the confederated king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, as also of higher and lower <hi>Austria,</hi> doe promise for Our selues, Our heires and succes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sors, without dissimulation, to vphold and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue (all the aforesaid Articles of this agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and confederated League, and all and eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry particular point therein contayned, as they are registred in the originall, word by word) willingly, and with a perpetuall, constant, and vniforme desire, and also promise that the same shall in like sort be vpholden and obserued, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantly,
<pb facs="tcp:177245:12"/>religiously, and inuiolably, as well as possible we can or may, and as firmely and reso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely, as if the same had <hi>verbatim</hi> beene de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed vpon, and publikely ordayned and confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med at the generall Parliament or meeting, of the Kingdome of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> the Margraueship of <hi>Morauia,</hi> the Dukedome of <hi>Silesia,</hi> the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graueship of higher and neather <hi>Lusatia,</hi> and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so of the higher and lower <hi>Austria;</hi> certainely hoping, that it will so fall out, that on the other side, the aforesaid confederated Lords haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined and decreed, all together, and euery one particularly, vprightly, constantly, and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giously, to obserue, vphold, and maintayne the same, and that with good neighbourhood, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>respondence, and vnitie, the same will daily more and more be strengthned, and firmly grounded; which Almightie God, Authour, encreaser, and protector of all lawfull contracts and confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racies, of his great mercy vouchsafe to graunt. And for the better and firmer witnessing of this perpetuall League, We haue here vnder subscri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed Our hands, and caused Our seales to bee thereunto annexed.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Giuen in the Castle of Prague, vpon the generall day of meeting of all the confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derated Kingdomes and Prouinces.<date> Anno 1620.</date>
               </dateline>
               <pb facs="tcp:177245:13"/>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>And wee, the aforesaid Ambassadors of the puisant King, and the famous Kingdome of <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemia,</hi> and of the incorporated Prouinces, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so of the lower <hi>Austria,</hi> with absolute and full power, being ordayned and deputed to bee at the consulting, treating, handling, and confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of this confederacie, approue all and euery particular things and points that are contayned in this accord of the perpetuall League, and in signe of our vndoubted fidelitie, beleeue and are perswaded, that by his Maiestie the King of <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemia,</hi> and the States of this Kingdome, and the confederated Prouinces thereof; the same shall by a speciall authentique Copie, vnder hand and seale, bee sent to the Prince and Kingdome of <hi>Hungaria</hi> and <hi>Transiluania,</hi> and to that end we haue hereunto put our hands and seales,</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>giuen in <hi>Presburg,</hi> in the open and generall meeting, <date>the 15. of Ianuarie 1620.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </postscript>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>